Okay, בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*, today's דף *Daf* is בבא בתרא *Bava
Batra* 146, but we actually are behind, so we pick up on
145B, קמ"ה עמוד ב' *Kuf Mem Hey Amud Bet*, about eight lines
down. We're talking about the institution of the שושבינות shoshvinos *Shoshbinut*, which
are these special types of groomsmen that you're expected to bring a
gift. And when you bring a gift and when you're a שושבין
*Shoshbin*, I guess, for somebody's wedding, then they become, then they have
to return that when they are your groomsmen, when they're one of
the שושבינות shoshvinos, *Shoshbinot* for your wedding. There's a real debt of
repaying that gift. Okay, so אמר רב כהנא *Amar Rav Kahana*, so
now we pick up eight lines down on קמ"ה עמוד ב' *Kuf
Mem Hey Amud Bet*. אמר רב כהנא *Amar Rav Kahana*, כללא דשושבינותא
*Klal de-shoshbinisa*, the general rule regarding the שושבינות *Shoshbinut* in terms of
what happens if you weren't at the wedding? Because the assumption is
you're going to invite me back to your wedding and then I
will repay the gift if I as a groomsman, but let's say
for some reason I'm not at the wedding. How does that play
out? So let's take a look. הוי במתא *Havi be-masa*, if you
were in the town when the wedding was taking place, איבעי ליה
למיתי *Iba-ei lei lemeisei*, you should have come. It seems like there
might not have been necessarily invited guests; it was just known the
wedding is happening and you should have come. So if you didn't
come, that's your fault and you don't get off from returning the
gift in that circumstance. שמע קול טבלא *Shama kol tavla*, now let's
say you weren't in the town, but there was, you know, the
drum was being beaten; apparently this was some way of letting the,
letting it know that a wedding was happening. So you somehow got
the message; you heard about the wedding. So similarly, איבעי ליה למיתי
*Iba-ei lei lemeisei*, so you should have, you should have come, and
the fact that you weren't there is not an excuse not to
repay the wedding gift. But here comes the real question: לא שמע
קול טבלא *Lo shama kol tavla*, you were out of town and
you did not hear the wedding drum; you didn't get invited. So
you would think reasonably you could say, 'Hey buddy, you didn't even
invite me to the wedding. You didn't tell me that it was
happening.' So you expect me now to repay a gift? The whole
idea here was about conviviality and about friendship, and if you're not
going to invite me to the wedding or let me know, like
you disinvited me,
but you didn't go out of your way to let me know,
and therefore I didn't know, why should I have to pay you
the gift? So surprisingly, you would think that's a pretty reasonable claim,
but surprisingly that is not the הלכה halacha *Halacha*. So the גמרא
Gemara
*Gemara* says, איבעי ליה לאודועיה *Iba-ei lei lo-odeiyei*, so yes, the groom
should have informed you. That was his bad; he had a responsibility
to inform you. תרעומת אית ליה *Tarumas it lei*, so you have
a complaint: 'How come you didn't invite me?' and, you know, 'I
would have wanted to be part of your wedding.' But even though
you have a complaint and you have a reason why you weren't
there, nevertheless שלומי משלם *Shalumei meshalem*, you do have a responsibility to
pay, to repay the gift that was given to you, even if
you weren't at the wedding. Okay, so that's really fascinating. You got
a gift, you have to repay it even though it didn't fit
in the structure of being at the wedding or not even knowing
or being invited; nevertheless you have to repay it. Now the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says, but what about the fact that had you been
at the wedding, you know, yes, you would have paid for a
gift, but you would have also gotten a nice smorg and a
meal and all of that? So can you deduct that from what
you are expected to pay back in the gift? When this guy
gave you his gift, you hosted him, you gave him a smorg
and a meal. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says.
So ועד כמה *Ve-ad kama*, so in that case when you weren't
at the wedding and presumably when you had a good reason when
it wasn't your fault that you weren't at the wedding, presumably we're
talking about the last case when you didn't know and you weren't
informed, so in that case do you really have to pay him
the full amount? So אמר אביי נהגו בני גנונא *Amar Abaye nahagu
benei ganuna*, the members of the wedding feast, the practice was עד
זוזא *Ad zuza*, if the cost of the שושבינות *Shoshbinut*, of the
gift, is up to a זוזא *Zuza*, then we would say אייתי
בכפי אכלי בכרסי *Aisei be-kapei, achlei be-charsei*, what you bring with your
hands you eat with your stomach. Meaning, so the assumption would be
that any gift up to a זוזא *Zuza*, you know, normally what
you would have eaten would have been worth at least a זוזא
*Zuza*, and therefore you do not have a responsibility now to give
a gift because that gift would have been, you would have gotten
it back in the food that you would have been fed, except
that you didn't get it because you weren't invited to the wedding.
Okay, so in that case you do not have to pay anything
back.
Now, עד ארבע משלם פלגא *Ad arba meshalem palga*, up to four
זוזא *Zuza*, if that was the size of the gift, then okay,
so now we're dealing with a little, the assumption here is also
that we're dealing that's a large gift, so the assumption is that
we're dealing with a little bit more of an expensive wedding, so
presumably you also would have been fed better. So in that case
you pay half the gift, half the size of the gift. If
this person gave you a, you know, a three זוזא *Zuza* gift,
then you give him back if you were not invited to the
wedding, you give him back one and a half. If, you know,
if he gave you a four or whatever, you give him back
two, because it's just assumed that that would have been the difference,
would have been the value up to half would have been the
value of the food. that you would have eaten at the wedding.
All right. ארבע משום פגם. מכאן ואילך, mikan va'eilach, איניש איניש כחשיבותיה.
inish inish k'chashivutei.
From that point on, everybody according to their like status. Okay. So,
so you know the way רשב"ם Rashbam just says, you basically based
on what the normal, you know, value of the food and of
the שמאָרג schmorg would have been and you deduct it and you
figure it out. So, yes you still owe it, but because you
were not aware of the wedding and had no reason to be
aware and it was their bad, you can deduct the cost of
what you would have been fed. All right, that makes it very
commercial, you know, obviously something that was done as a practice of,
like I said, a friendship and so on, but you know that's
the way the nature that this institution took place. All right, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this: תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our
Rabbis taught: עשה עמו בפומבי וביקש לעשות עמו בצינא. Asa imo bifumbi
ubikesh la'asot imo betzina.
When you invited your friend for your wedding, you know, it was
a big public wedding, huge feast, 300 people invited, and now he
wants to do it as a small little private wedding in the
backyard. יכול לומר לו בפומבי אעשה עמך כדרך שעשית עמי. Yachol lomar
lo bifumbi esseh imach kederach she'asita imi.
You could say back to him, look, you know, I want to,
I'll pay you back in a similar type of a wedding. I
made a big public wedding and you were part of a huge
big fancy feast. So if, you know, that's the type of circumstances
where I will repay the gift, if you get married in that
way, not if you get married in this way. And not everybody
has the money to get married in that way,
but
but nevertheless, that's the reality. There has to be a certain like
equal reciprocity. And if not, he can say, I don't want to
be your groomsman, and or I don't have responsibility to function as
your groomsman in a non-equal wedding and therefore presumably I'm off from
giving the gift, which is interesting. Okay, not so fair for people
of different means, but that's the way it is. All right, אעשה
עמך כדרך שעשית עמי. esseh imach kederach she'asita imi. עשה עמו בבתולה
וביקש לעשות עמו באלמנה. Asa imo bivtulah ubikesh la'asot imo be'almanah. Now
you invited your friend over to your wedding when it was a
first wedding, he got married and it was a second wedding, you
know, he was marrying a widow. יכול לומר לו בבתולה אעשה עמך
כדרך שעשית עמי. Yachol lomar lo bivtulah esseh imach kederach she'asita imi.
I'll be your groomsman when you get, when you have a, you
know, marry somebody a woman for whom it's their first wedding. Since
this is a different type of a wedding, that's not an equivalent
scenario. So again, all this does seem to be a little petty,
but you know, it's not saying that people would not actually serve
as groomsmen in all of that. It's when it turns into a
legal court case and it's about actually suing for the gift, then
the actual sort of legal responsibility is only in an equivalent type
of a scenario. Okay. עשה עמו בשניה וביקש לעשות עמו בראשונה. Asa
imo bishniyah ubikesh la'asot imo berishonah.
Now
how about the reverse? Let's say the guy's wedding that he invited
you to was a second marriage and, and I know, I mean
I'm sorry, you had him over for your wedding, it was a
second marriage for you and now he wants to invite you over
for his first marriage. יכול לומר לו לכשתשא אשה אחרת אעשה עמך.
Yachol lomar lo lichshe'tissa ishah acheret esseh imach. So when you get,
have a your second marriage, I mean the first one was about
first and second for the woman's perspective, this is first and second
from the man's perspective. So even if his, if his wedding is
a bigger deal than your wedding, presumably if first wedding will be
a bigger deal, you can say look, it doesn't matter, it's not
equivalent, I don't have a legal responsibility for a non-equivalent wedding. Quite
fascinating. Okay,
all of these, you know, requirements sort of, you know, seem to
sort of be narrowing the circumstances under which this would apply. But
okay, where were we? עשה עמו באחת וביקש לעשות עמו בשתים. Asa
imo be'achat ubikesh la'asot imo bishtayim. Now he
came,
he came to your wedding and you were only marrying one woman,
now he is getting married to two women. That's a little bit
of what it sounds like, like two women at the same time.
Okay, so there's a little question about how to read that but
certainly that's sort of the simple read of it. יכול לומר לו
באחת אעשה עמך כדרך שעשית עמי. Yachol lomar lo be'achat esseh imach
kederach she'asita imi.
No, only if you're marrying one woman will I get married to
you, not if you're marrying two women, will I serve as your
groomsman, do I have a legal obligation to serve as your groomsman?
Okay, we get the idea. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, because we're talking
about, you know, I guess different levels, it's not exactly clear why
we're going to enter why we're sort of teaching this piece of
גמרא Gemara right now that we're about to teach, but maybe again
because we're talking about like wealth and different levels of wealth and
so on. But let's take a look at what this גמרא Gemara.
says. Quite fascinating a גמרא Gemara about the, about the you know
about like metaphors for different types of sages. Okay, so let's take
a look.
תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our Rabbis taught: אוצר נכסים אוצר פומבי, Otzar
nechasim otzar pumbi, if somebody is wealthy in property and wealthy like
in, you know sort of and is wealthy in a public arena,
so the רשב"ם Rashbam says it means has a lot of landed
property. and has a lot of animals and flocks and everybody sort
of is well aware of their wealth. So what type of, that's
a metaphor for what type of a scholar? זהו בעל אגדות. Zehu
baal aggadot. That is somebody that is a good at אגדה aggadah
or we might say he's good at giving sermons, popular lectures, you
know, everybody appreciates what they have to say, comes out, he gives
beautiful sermons that's inspiring to hundreds, to thousands of people, okay, the
תורה Torah is very, very accessible. So that person, his quality, the
wares of his תורה Torah is seen and appreciated by all. That's
like somebody who is wealthy and their wealth is known and seen
by all. All right, so that's that.
עתיר סלעים עתיר תקוע, Atir sela'im atir takua, somebody who is rich
in coins and תקוע, takua, interesting question of exactly what תקוע takua
means here. You know, the רשב"ם Rashbam says that it means it
could mean that he's got a lot of houses, that's not so
clear about how that would exactly fit, and you know,
he has a couple of possible explanations, another one is that it
means that he's rich in oil because תקוע Takua is a name
of a place oil would come from. But anyway, this is, let's
focus rather on the idea about the coins, okay, so this person
has a lot of wealth but it's not exposed for people to
see. He's a coin changer, it comes out when people have to
change money with it. Okay, so in that type of a case,
so what's
so what's that? זה בעל פלפול. Ze baal pilpul. This is somebody
of פלפול. pilpul. פלפול Pilpul nowadays has a negative connotation, but in
the גמרא Gemara. it meant somebody of like profound analytic ability. So
this is a type of a person, you know, they're brilliant, but
they're not going around giving דרשות, drashot, and it's not like everybody
sees it and everybody wants to hear the most intact analysis of
a דף גמרא. daf Gemara. But when you speak to them in
learning, you're like whoa, I really appreciate what he has to say.
So you know when like when you need to change your money
and the money changer takes out his money, then you really sort
of you know see what they've got. Okay, so that's that person.
Where were we? עתיר משח עתיר כמס. Atir mashach atir kamas. So
again, two words that are not so clear. The רשב"ם Rashbam reads
it, משח mashach could mean oil, but the רשב"ם Rashbam reads it
as somebody in things that are very like are measured, measurable types
of things,
and so he sort of says like grain, it's not exactly clear
how he gets it to mean sort of like grain that you
store up in a storehouse. The clearer word here is some say
it means oil, the clearer word here is כמס, kamas, stuff that's
stored. So this is like you've got a lot of stored wares,
all right? Now, and so and in that, let's see what it's
being compared to. זהו בעל שמועות. Zehu baal shmuot. That is somebody
that knows many, many teachings, right? Like a memorizer, the person like
who's a walking encyclopedia. So what's the difference of the metaphor here?
Well, the person who has money that is invested, that's not necessarily
public and people don't see, so that money is actually, you know,
generating more wealth. That was the first case, you know, the money
changer, the person maybe that has rental properties, they're generating a lot
of wealth, and then you sort of see it when you need
to go ahead and to change money or you know to engage
them. This is a person that has a lot of stored up
funds, all right? They've got a lot of storehouses, but they're not
generating any wealth, but they're just able to produce it when needed.
And that is the person who has a lot of knowledge, you
know, a lot of sort of fact knowledge, erudite, but not necessarily
פלפול, pilpul, not necessarily analytic intelligence, you know, to analyze to come
up with new ideas and so on. Okay, that's somebody that's got
a lot of stored wares. הכל צריכים למרי חטיא, Hakol tzrichim lemarei
chittaya, גמרא. Gemara
Now this seems to actually be another a different line that the
גמרא Gemara has somewhere else that's sort of been like spliced in.
There's a line that everybody needs the person with, with,
who has the wheat. And this is גמרא. Gemara So what does
that mean? That means that, that the גמרא Gemara sort of in
one place asks like which is better? עוקר הרים Oker harim or
סיני? Sinai? The person, exactly this question, the person who has the
analytic ability or the one who, that's the עוקר הרים oker harim
lifting up mountains, or the one who, it's like they received the
תורה Torah at הר סיני, Har Sinai, they have all of the
knowledge but not necessarily analytic ability. And the גמרא Gemara says, הכל
צריכים למרי חטיא. Hakol tzrichim lemarei chittaya.
Everybody needs the one with the wheat because the idea is, you
know, to learn אגירסא לגרוס agirsa ligros is also like to grind,
right? You like you turn the wheat into flour, you and then
the flour into bread, right? But that's your analysis, you break it
down, you crush it, you develop it and so on. So that's
all great, but you can't get there until you start with the
wheat, you need to know the facts before you start speculating and
so on. So that's that. So that's a point the גמרא Gemara
made here, you know, it's sort of it plays a little to
like the פלפול pilpul versus the שמועות. shmuot. But so another line
that sort of is parallel to the בעל שמועות, ba'al shmuot, the
person with the facts, is acknowledging everybody needs the guy with the
wheat. All right, you know, might not be that it doesn't, it
doesn't increase the, you know, his own knowledge, it's stable, it's but
nevertheless it is the most essential, you have to start with that.
All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this and that's
okay,
where were we? So now the גמרא Gemara continues, I mean the
רשב"ם Rashbam says it sounds like גמרא Gemara. is a little bit
more the actual analysis, but that doesn't you know, but that doesn't
fit with the normal statement of the גמרא Gemara about הכל צריכים
למרי חטיא. hakol tzrichim lemarei chittaya. But גמרא Gemara often does mean
more the analysis, so it's not a little, not totally clear how
those pieces are being fit together in this גמרא. Gemara All right,
אמר רב זירא אמר רב. Amar Rav Zeira amar Rav. מאי דכתיב,
Mai d'ichtiv, what's meant by the פסוק? pasuk? כל ימי עני רעים,
Kol yimei ani ra'im, all of the days of
a poor person are evil. So what's, you know, what's really being
meant by this? Here the גמרא Gemara is going to really understand
that גמרא Gemara, means like the analysis. Okay. So it says, so
what is meant that all the days of a poor person are
evil? זה בעל גמרא. Ze ba'al Gemara. That is the person who
focuses on analysis, and because you're constantly banging your head against a
wall trying to figure it out and do all the Talmudic, you
know, ins and outs and so on.
וטוב לב משתה תמיד, V'tov lev mishteh tamid, and a good heart
is like constantly, you know, of like inebriated and drinking. So what
does that mean? Because it's not exactly parallel, right? If it said
the days of the poor are terrible and the days of the
rich are wonderful. So what does it mean for the good-hearted it's
always a feast? So what does that refer to? וטוב לב משתה
תמיד זה בעל משנה. V'tov lev mishteh tamid ze ba'al Mishnah. That's
a guy that all he has to do is worry about the
actual facts, what were the teachings, and not bother about the analysis.
He's happy, he doesn't have to think too hard, he just memorizes
it all, he's got a very nice easy type of a life.
Okay. רבא אמר איפכא, Rava amar ipcha, the reverse. No, because you
know the person that knows the גמרא Gemara ultimately is going to
be able to come to a conclusion and know what the הלכה
halacha. is, and that's very gratifying, and he knows how to act.
The person with, so that's the וטוב לב משתה תמיד. v'tov lev
mishteh tamid. He's always in a good mood at least for where
he's able to reach. The person who's all of his days are
bad is the person only knows משנה. Mishnah. They're not going to
act properly because they don't really know the הלכה. halacha
והיינו דאמר רב משרשיא משמיה דרבא. V'hainu d'amar Rav Mesharshaya mishmei d'Rava.
That's what רב משרשיא Rav Mesharshaya said in the name of רבא.
Rava. מאי דכתיב, Mai d'ichtiv, what is meant by the פסוק? pasuk?
מסיע אבנים יעצב בהם, Massia avanim ye'atzev bahem, the one who carries
stones will be saddened by them. בוקע עצים יסכן בם, Bokei'a etzim
yissachen bam, and the one who uses wood, chops wood, will be
heated by it. מסיע אבנים יעצב בהם אלו בעלי משנה. Massia avanim
ye'atzev bahem elu ba'alei Mishnah. The one that lifts stones will be,
you know, troubled by them, anguished by them. That is the people
of the משנה. Mishnah. They're carrying all of this weight, all of
this knowledge, but it causes them anguish because, or it should cause
them anguish, ultimately it'll be, it'll be, you know, disappointing because it,
it doesn't lead to knowing actually what the הלכה halacha is. אלו
בעלי משנה. Elu ba'alei Mishnah. בוקע עצים יסכן בם, Bokei'a etzim yissachen
bam, but if you chop the wood, you get warmed by it.
אלו בעלי גמרא. Elu ba'alei Gemara. That's the people of the גמרא
Gemara again, it's that's the chopping. It's not just the knowledge, it's
the grinding, it's the chopping, it produces energy and heat and warmth
and it shows you ultimately, you know, what the right הלכה halacha,
is. Okay. רבי חנינא אמר כל ימי עני רעים זה שיש לו
אשה רעה. Rabbi Chanina amar kol yimei ani ra'im ze she'yesh lo
isha ra'ah. Now we're switching gears. All the day of a poor
person are are wicked, that's a man who has a bad wife.
This is the men of the גמרא, Gemara, you know, complaining about
about women. So וטוב לב משתה תמיד זה שיש לו אשה טובה.
V'tov lev mishteh tamid ze she'yesh lo isha tova. That's if you
have a good wife. Fine. רבי ינאי אמר כל ימי עני רעים
זה איסטניס. Rabbi Yannai amar kol yimei ani ra'im ze istenis. All
the days of the poor person are evil, that is talking about
somebody that is very finicky, you know, very easily like everything has
to be exactly in a particular way. If there's a little bit
of a mess, they get so angry and so upset and it's
so disturbing to them, so they're always in anguish because nothing is
ever perfect, everything sets them off. וטוב לב משתה תמיד זה שדעתו
יפה. V'tov lev mishteh tamid ze she'da'ato yaffa. And וטוב לב משתה
תמיד, v'tov lev mishteh tamid, that is a person who's like easygoing,
it doesn't matter, okay, a little dirt, a little mess, whatever, that
person's got it easy in life, things don't bother them. All right.
רבי יוחנן אמר כל ימי עני רעים זה רחמן. Rabbi Yochanan amar
kol yimei ani ra'im ze rachman. That is a somebody who is
overly, you know, too compassionate, too empathic, feels too much, you know,
their heart goes out to everybody, they don't have a good filter,
they're not able to protect themselves. So that person is always, you
know, feeling other people's pain. וטוב לב משתה תמיד זה אכזרי, V'tov
lev mishteh tamid ze achzari, is a very ironic read. Good heart
is constantly in a is a
feast is a cruel... you know, and but it's somebody, you know,
making a point that if you are not sensitive to other people,
you go around life happy. You're not feeling other people's pains. Obviously,
there's a balance here about protecting yourself but being sensitive enough so
that you're able to help other people and empathize and so on.
Okay, רבי יהושע בן לוי אומר כל ימי עני רעים זה שדעתו
קצרה וטוב לב משתה תמיד זה שדעתו רחבה. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi
omer kol yimei ani ra'im zeh she'da'ato ketzarah v'tov lev mishteh tamid
zeh she'da'ato rechavah. Sounds similar to before: narrow versus broad, you know,
but what does that mean? That, you know, also somebody who is
very, you know, very like, you know, jealous and ungenerous and like
it's always upset why does that person have more than me?
Constantly has all of those senses they've been, you know, they've been
done an injustice, as opposed to somebody that's a very generous spirit,
giving spirit oh, it's so wonderful, that person has it so lovely.
All right, I didn't get the raise, but they got the raise,
it's so lovely for them. Okay, that also somebody will be constantly
in a... so different type of a disposition. Based on your various
dispositions, how you go through life. Are you going through life sort
of happy or miserable? You might also speak about the optimist and
the pessimist. I once had a debate with my wife about, you
know, she's the... she's very much the pessimist, I'm very much the
optimist and, you know, and I said to her, you know, like,
like,
I might be wrong a lot of the time with my optimism,
but like, I go through, you know, I go through my life
happy. So if it doesn't work out, you know, I... most of
my time, you know, I'm optimistic, so at least I'm going through
my life happy. And she says, yeah, but I'm never disappointed when
it doesn't work out. So different ways of going through life. All
right, anyway, but that was interesting. I really don't know what that
had so much to do with the גמרא Gemara we're at the
top of that we were doing before. Also interesting the way the
גמרא Gemara compared מרי חטיא, Mori Chitaya, the master of wheat, to
גמרא, Gemara, which often מרי חטיא Mori Chitaya is more compared to
the person who just has the storage, has the knowledge, but not
necessarily the analysis.
Top of קמ"ו עמוד א'. Kuf Mem Vav amud alef. אמר רבי
יהושע בן לוי כל ימי
עני רעים Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi kol yimei ani ra'im all
the days of a poor person are evil. ואיכא שבתות וימים טובים?
V'ika Shabbasos v'Yomim Tovim?
How can you say all the days? At least on שבתות Shabbasos
and ימים טובים, Yomim Tovim, you know, a person has some good
food and they get a little bit of a
respite. Maybe the people of the גבאי צדקה gabbai tzedakah give them
food for שבת. Shabbos. So, כשמואל k'Shmuel like שמואל, Shmuel, דאמר שמואל
שינוי וסת תחלת חולי. d'amar Shmuel shinui vest techilas choli. No, even
שבת Shabbos and יום טוב Yom Tov is a problem for them
as well because just having good food on שבת Shabbos is changing
the norm, and changing the norm, you know, when you change your
norms of your diet, that can also lead to sickness and illness
and so on. Okay, so even those days are not good. The
גמרא Gemara ends this discussion by saying: כתיב בספר בן סירא K'siv
b'sefer Ben Sira and though בן סירא Ben Sira is one of
the ספרים חיצוניים, Sefarim Chitzonim, sometimes the גמרא Gemara quotes it. It's
written in the book of בן סירא: Ben Sira: כל ימי עני
רעים Kol yimei ani ra'im that's sort of citing the verse from
משלי. Mishlei. ובן סירא אומר U'Ben Sira omer but בן סירא Ben
Sira says: אף לילות Af leilos not only the days of a
poor person. You would think at night they're asleep, so a poor
person and a rich person, you know, when they're asleep at night,
there's no real difference. No, even the nights of a poor person
are evil. Why? בשפל גגין גגו Bishfal gagin gago so their roof
is lower than everybody else's roof in the town, so ממטר גגין
לגגו mimatar gagin l'gago all of the rain from everybody else's roof,
you know, like runs down onto his roof and he's constantly having
leaks in his roof and so on. So even at night. ברום
הרים כרמו מעפר כרמו לכרמים B'rum harim karmo me'afar karmo l'charamim and
his vineyard is at the top of the mountain and all of
his good, you know, soil trickles down to the vineyards below him.
So even at night when he's asleep, his nights are, you know,
are evil, you know, are bad, while those of the rich people
are good. All right, that was a fascinating end. I assume it
has something to do with the fact that we're talking about different
levels of wealth in terms of the שושבינות or different types of
weddings. Next משנה: Mishnah: השולח סבלונות. Ha'shole'ach savlonos. Now we move from
שושבינות, which is the groomsmen, to סבלונות. savlonos. סבלונות Savlonos are traditional
gifts that were given from the groom to the bride and the
bride's family after the קידושין kiddushin before the נישואין. nissuim.
So somebody who sends these סבלונות, savlonos, these gifts, לבית חמיו l'veis
chamiv to his father-in-law's house. שלח שם מאה מנה Shelach sham me'ah
maneh he sent them worth a hundred מנה. maneh. ואכל שם סעודת
חתן V'achal sham seudas chasan and he goes there and they have
a nice little, you know, ווארט vort and an engagement party I
mean, קידושין kiddushin already took place, but you know, eating there in
some type of a way that's celebrating the marriage. אפילו
בדינר אין נגבין Afillu b'dinar ein nigbin even
if
it only cost one דינר, dinar, you know, and this was worth
a hundred מנה, maneh, nevertheless, once they had he had a meal,
then you can no longer... and then if something happens and the
wedding doesn't go through, now there's already been קידושין, kiddushin, but... The
נישואין nissuin doesn't go through, either there's a divorce, or one of
the parties die, or something like that, he cannot ask for them
to be returned. Once there was some celebrating of it, it's considered
to be that, you know, he is basically just writing off, you
know, giving them fully to the bride and the bride's family. Now
we'll see in the גמרא, Gemara the גמרא Gemara will make a
distinction about, you know, different circumstances and different types of gift, gifts
that normally would be used up before the wedding would take place,
again, before the נישואין, nissuin, I'll speak more specifically, take place, or
gifts that would usually come with her when the נישואין nissuin took
place and be brought back into the marriage, maybe those make a
difference. But anyway, at least the משנה Mishnah saying straight, they can
keep the gifts. Okay. Once there was some celebration, it seemed like
he just gives it over fully.
לא אכל סעודת חתן. Lo achal seudat chatan. However, they did not
have the meal.
הרי אלו נגבין, Harei elu nigbin, then and some one side dies,
or maybe there even was a divorce, although then maybe question whose
fault the divorce was, but anyway,
then if there was nothing that sort of like created that finality
to it, then it's still seen as like tentative whether this will
resolve, you know, resolve in the actual נישואין, nissuin, even though the
קידושין kiddushin took place. So then if it doesn't play out, he
can collect those gifts back. שלח סבלונות מרובים שיחזרו עמה לבית בעלה
הרי אלו נגבין. Shalach sevlonot merubim she'yachzeru ima l'veit ba'ala harei elu
nigbin. If he sent many gifts, like a large סבלונות, sevlonot, that
it was understood that they would come back to him when she,
you know, when she got married, then he can collect them.
סבלונות מועטים שתשתמש בהן בבית אביה, Sevlonot muatim she'tishtamesh bahen b'veit aviha,
but if they were small amount that it was understood that they
would be used up when she was still in her father's house
before the נישואין, nissuin, then אינם נגבין, einam nigbin, they are not
collected. Now, it's very unclear what the exact circumstances are, right? First
of all, like, you know,
I mean the big question is, are we talking here that they
did, that he did have the סעודת חתן seudat chatan or did
not have the סעודת חתן? seudat chatan? Is it even within the
case of not having the סעודת חתן seudat chatan it makes a
difference if there are a lot or a little? Does it have
to be explicitly spelled out that the intent was to bring it
back, you know, to the חתן's chatan house or to use it?
Or is what the משנה Mishnah saying that the assumption is if
they were a lot, the intent was to bring it back, and
if it were a little, the intent was to bring it when
they got married, and if it was a little, the intent was
to be used? What if it's a medium amount? What if you
don't know? So a lot of things that are unclear about how
to read the end part of the משנה Mishnah with the beginning.
Let's see if the גמרא Gemara can help clarify all of this.
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, says רבא. Rava. דווקא דינר, Davka dinar, we're
only talking about a דינר. dinar. אבל פחות מדינר לא, Aval pachot
mi'dinar lo, but if he ate less than a דינר, dinar, even
though they had the סעודת חתן, seudat chatan, then the gifts are
not final, and if something happens and the נישואין nissuin doesn't take
place, he can take the gifts back. So the גמרא Gemara says:
פשיטא דינר תנן, Pshita dinar tnan, obviously it says a
דינר. dinar. לא מהו דתימא הוא הדין אפילו פחות מדינר, Lo mahu
detaima hu hadin afilu pachot mi'dinar, no, maybe דינר dinar was not
דווקא, davka, maybe even less than a דינר. dinar. והאי דקתני דינר
אורחא דמילתא קתני, V'hai d'katani dinar orcha d'milta katani, and the fact
that it says דינר dinar is just to tell you, yeah, no,
that's like a normal way of speaking, to contrast it to מאה
מנה. meah maneh. קא משמע לן, Ka mashma lan, that it's exactly
a דינר. dinar. Now there's also the reason to think the משנה
Mishnah might not have meant an exact דינר, dinar, because it was
contrasted with a case of not eating a סעודת חתן. seudat chatan.
It should have been contrasted with a case of not eating a
דינר's dinar worth of a סעודת חתן. seudat chatan. So the משנה
Mishnah actually told two extremes and didn't discuss the middle. You eat
a סעודת חתן seudat chatan with a דינר, dinar, the gifts are
given over finally, and if you don't eat a סעודת חתן, seudat
chatan, they're not given over. What if you had a סעודת חתן
seudat chatan less than a דינר? dinar? So רבא Rava says that's
like not eating a סעודת חתן, seudat chatan, and you can then
get the gifts back if something happens and נישואין nissuin does not
take place. Okay, let's see if this is going to remain clear.
אכל
תנן. Achal tnan. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: The
משנה Mishnah says if you ate a סעודת חתן, seudat chatan, that's
when the gifts are given over. שתה מאי? Shata mai? Let's say
you only had a drink at their house. הוא
תנן?
Hu
tnan? It says that, you know, he ate. שלוחו מאי? Shlucho mai?
So let's say that, where was it? It doesn't,
right, it doesn't actually say the word הוא, hu, but it meant
he, the one who sent, the groom ate the סעודה. seuda. Let's
say the groom wasn't the one who ate the סעודה, seuda, but
somebody representing the groom went there and was part of the wedding
party. What would be the story there?
Okay. שם תנן? Sham tnan? שגר לו מאי? Shagar lo mai? It
says that he ate, he participated in the wedding party there, at
the father-in-law's house. Let's say they were having a wedding party at
the house and they sent him, you know, he didn't come to
the meal, the groom, but they sent him, you know, a doggy
bag, they sent... sent him food from the meal, and he ate
it in his house. Would that count as participating in the wedding
party to make the gift final? Okay, שגר לו מאי. Shagar lo
mai. So we don't know the answer to any of these. Let's
see. תא שמע, Ta shma, come in here. דאמר רב יהודה אמר
שמואל, De'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, Rav יהודה Yehuda says in the
name of שמואל, Shmuel, מעשה באדם אחד ששיגר לבית חמיו מאה קרונות
של כדי יין ושל כדי שמן, ma'aseh be'adam echad sheshigar leveit chamiv
me'ah kronot shel kadei yayin veshel kadei shemen, a certain person sent
to his father-in-law's house a hundred horns, like a hundred, you know,
flasks of oil and of wine, ושל כלי כסף ושל כלי זהב,
veshel klei chesef veshel klei zahav, silver and gold vessels, ושל כלי
מילת, veshel klei milat, and silk,
ורכב בשמחתו, verachav besimchato, and when he was riding, I was going
to say, ורכב, verachev, he also sent them a car, no, but
anyway, that's a little anachronistic, anyway, ורכב בשמחתו, verachav besimchato, and he
rode on his horse in his joy, והלך ועמד על פתח בית
חמיו, vehalach ve'amad al petach beit chamiv, and he stood by the
doorway of his father-in-law's house, והוציאו לו כוס של חמין, vehotziu lo
kos shel chamin, and they brought him out, you know, before he
had a chance to walk in the door, a nice hot cup
of tea, ושתה, veshata, and he drank, ומת, vamet, and he died
right there on the doorstep.
Okay, וזו הלכה העלה רב אחא סרביא לשני חכמים באושא, vezo halacha
he'ela Rav Acha Sarbiya lishnei chachamim be'Usha, this הלכה, halacha this case,
the question of the הלכה halacha? was brought by, you know, this
רב אחא סרביא Rav Acha Sarbiya to the sages in אושא, Usha,
which is where the Sanhedrin was, and said what's the story? Is
the סבלנות savlanot gift, this extremely expensive gift that he sent, is
that final? He died, but he didn't actually eat, he only drank,
he only whatever, what's the הלכה? halachic ואמרו, ve'amru, and they said,
סבלנות העשויות לבלות אין נגבין ושאינן עשויות לבלות נגבין. savlanot ha'asuyot livlot
ein nigbin veshe'einan asuyot livlot nigbin. So now we're, by the way,
making a distinction which is sort of a different version of the
end of our משנה mishnah and saying the types of סבלנות savlanot
that are normally will be worn out, will be normally used up
before the נישואין nisuin takes place, you know, that obviously would be
food, could be clothes that would get worn, could be, you know,
could even be money that would get spent. All those types of
stuff, you know, don't, you don't get to take back. However, the
stuff that is אינן עשויות לבלות, einan asuyot livlot, stuff that would
definitely last until the נישואין, nisuin, you know, a pearl necklace, so
you're going to, you're sending it to your, this woman that you
are מאורס me'oras to, and you're expecting that when there's a נישואין,
nisuin, she'll still have the pearl necklace and bring it back into
the marriage at the time of the נישואין. nisuin. So that type
of a thing, even when you are entitled to get the gifts
back or whatever your family, the guy died or whatever, but, you
know, even when you're entitled to get the gifts back, wait, I
said it the wrong way, even when you're not entitled to get
the gifts back, you still are entitled to get back the things
that are אינן עשויות לבלות. einan asuyot livlot. The things that were
given once you had that meal at the, at the, at the
house of the bride, of of the father-in-law's house, then any, then
the gift was final for anything that was assumed that would get
used up, you know? But anything that you were expecting that was
going to be brought back into the marriage, even that would never
be final. That would always have an opportunity to take back if
the נישואין nisuin did not get complete. Okay, so that is taking,
before we get on to these questions about אכל achal and שתה,
shata, the end of the משנה, mishnah, the distinction between big סבלנות
savlanot or little סבלנות, savlanot, reconceptualizing it from big and little to
will they get used up in the כלה's kalla house or not,
which is sort of indicated at the end of the משנה. mishnah.
And then saying that distinction obtains even when the gift is final.
Even when the gift is final and he ate בבית חמיו, beveit
chamiv, okay, nevertheless, the stuff that he was expecting that would always
come back after the נישואין, nisuin, that stuff still does revert to
him. So what's the upshot here? They made this distinction between עשויות
לבלות asuyot livlot and אינן עשויות לבלות, einan asuyot livlot, but the
stuff that was עשויות לבלות, asuyot livlot, that was final, okay, because
he had this drink at the, at the, you know, door, you
know, right at the door, right at the porch of his father-in-law's
house, that made it like the סעודת חתן se'udat chatan and the
gift was final, which applies to עשויות לבלות, asuyot livlot, things that
were going to get used up. So that should resolve a lot
of our question,
okay? שמע מינה אפילו שתה, Shma mina afilu shata, from here we
can infer even not eating, even drinking, that definitely we can infer.
You don't have to specifically eat. שמע מינה אפילו פחות מדינר, Shma
mina afilu pachot midinar, we also see this a contradiction to what
רבא Rava said. It was just a cup of hot water, so
even less than
a דינר. dinar. Okay? So אמר רב אשי, amar Rav Ashi, so
רב אשי Rav Ashi said, man, not
necessarily, מאן לימא לן דלא שחקי ליה מרגניתא דשויא אלפא זוזי ואשקיה.
man leima lan dela shachki lei marganita deshvya alfa zuzei ve'ashkeih. No,
who knows, maybe it was a drink that was worth a דינר?
dinar? Who's telling you they didn't grind up a pearl and, you
know, he drank this pearl juice, you know, in the liquid? Which
seems crazy, the רשב"ם Rashbam claims well maybe that was a type
of a special רפואה, refuah, you know, a belief to be type
of a medicine or something. But what One wonders if what רב
אשי Rav Ashi is saying is like even if it's absurd, you
never know. But okay, if you say you need a דינר, dinar,
but then you could always say who’s to say that there weren't
gold scrapings in it and it effectively makes the דינר dinar rule
no longer effective. Anyway, but the it sounds like we don't require
a דינר dinar although the Gemara's trying to insist that we do.
All right.
Now, ושמע מינה, ushma mina, you also heard from this, אפילו שיגרו
ליה, afilu shigru lei, even if you don't eat it at the
house of the father-in-law, even if you eat it outside the house
of the father-in-law. Now that seems a little debatable, talk about a
liminal case. So the Gemara says no, דילמא כל פתח בית חמיך
כבית חמיך דמי. dilma kol petach beit chamich kebeit chamich dami. That
we're not so sure. Maybe right at the door front of your
father's house is like your father's house. It doesn't really tell you
what it would be when it was nowhere in the environs of
your, I mean, of your father-in-law's house. Okay, so what have we
said? We said that when there's a meal, the gift is final,
the סבלונות savlonot is final, for the סבלונות savlonot that are not
expected to be brought back when the נישואין nisuin takes place. Those
that are עשויין ליבלות. asuyin livalot.
And when and now we've raised some questions. The statement that it
has to be a דינר, dinar, a full דינר, dinar, anything less
no good, although that was called into question. It's clear that not
necessarily eating, even drinking. What's not clear is, does it have to
be in the father-in-law's house or not? Let's now take a look
at a whole other series of questions. איבעיא להו, ibaya lehu, they
raised the following question. מהו שישולש? mahu sheyisholash? What's the story about
thirding it? Now שישולש sheyisholash is a way of saying like making
it proportional. So the way the רשב"ם Rashbam and תוספות Tosafot explain
this question is if it wasn't, if we buy into the idea
that it has to be a דינר, dinar, let's say you only
ate a half a דינר. dinar. Do they get to keep half
of the gift? Would we make it proportional to this דינר dinar
requirement? All right, that's a little bizarre. What's this magic of דינר?
dinar? But okay.
I mean, שבח סבלונות מהו? shevach savlonot mahu? Now how about a
different question? Let's say that the סבלונות savlonot improved. You are going
now to take them back because they are, you did not eat
this סעודת חתן. seudat chatan. So, you know, you're taking them back.
What is the story now if they're now worth more than when
you sent them? Who gets that increased value? All right? מהו? mahu?
כיון דאינהו לדידיה הדרי ברשותיה שבח? keivan deinhu ledidei hadri birshutei shevach?
Do we say that since if they're around, they're coming back to
you, you're getting them back because these are not עשויין ליבלות asuyin
livalot or because, you know, it's whatever, it was a case that
you didn't eat the סעודת חתן? seudat chatan? So therefore they always
are considered to be yours still and it's your property that's improving?
או דילמא, o dilma, or do we say, כיון דאי אבדו או
איגנבו בעי שלומי ליה, keivan de'i avdu o ignavu ba'ei shalumei lei,
since if they got stolen or lost, right, then then and again
it was a scenario where then they had to get returned, then
the bride's family would have to compensate you for that, pay it
up? So ברשותא דידה שבחו. birshuta didah shevachu. So then it really
shows that it's in her ownership it improved and not in your
ownership. And the Gemara says תיקו. teiku. Now conceptually this is really
like a really key question and it's going to get even more
interesting in a minute when we deal with,
excuse me, what I meant to say is like we actually dealt
with this yesterday which in the case of like the wedding ring.
All right, and
which is, do we conceptualize these things that go back as they're
a definite gift but there's some some assumption that it has to
be repaid but they're definitely owned by the bride? Or do we
consider them to be a sort of like of a tentative gift?
You know, in the case of the כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin from
yesterday, and there's a whole major discussion, issue this comes up in
secular law all the time about if a wedding doesn't go through,
do you have to return the engagement ring? And there are some
place, the general rule is it depends who was at fault for
the breakup, but it's very state by state. And some states say
like there's been some ruling like no, it was definitely given and
it's for you to keep end of story and then, always it's
a final gift and you know some the opposite, always it's never
a final gift, doesn't matter whose fault it was, it always has
to get returned.
The always final gift is a really rare outlier. Okay, but all
of these cases, the question is is it like a מתנה בתנאי?
matana betnai? You know? Because if that were true you would never
need a גט get from אירוסין, eirusin, right? I mean if the
wedding doesn't go through and there's no נישואין nisuin and you have
to give back the כסף קידושין, kesef kiddushin, then there was never
any כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin that was given. So it doesn't really,
that's the Gemara about like you know, לטיבויי ניתנו letivuyei nitnu that
we dealt with the other day. So it seems more like no,
it is an absolute gift and nevertheless there's an idea that if
the נישואין nisuin doesn't go through, there's an expectation that you reimburse.
It's a little bizarre. It's not a תנאי, tnai, it is an
absolute gift, but there's still this expectation, so or this obligation. So
here too that's the question the גמרא Gemara asks. When the סבלונות
savlanos don't remain final and they go back, was it that it
really belonged to the bride's family and now they're just paying back?
And if that's true the bride's family gets the increase in value?
Or is it that no, it never really left the groom's family,
the groom until the נישואין nissuin takes place and therefore it's his
property that improved in value. Very parallel to the discussion yesterday.
Okay, let's take a look.
Now,
where were we? תיקו. Teyku. בעי רבא. Ba'ei Rava. רבא Rava asks.
סבלונות העשוין לבלות ולא בלו מהו? Savlanos ha'asuyin livalos velo balu mahu?
When we say that it's things that normally would get worn out—food,
clothing, maybe even
cash—and that those don't go back if there was a סעודת חתן.
seudas chasan.
So what if we mean that that's just the genre of gifts
they are? What if it was all that stuff but it didn't
get worn out and it's still in good shape? Maybe those do
have to go back. Now that's not what it sounded like. It
sounded like that was the expectation they were going to stay with
the bride's family, they don't go back when there was a סעודת
חתן. seudas chasan. But he says, I'm not so sure. What's the
story if they didn't get worn out and they're still around? Maybe
they, what's the story? מהו? Mahu? תא שמע, Ta shema, come and
hear. וזו הלכה העלה רבי אלעזר ברבי לפני חכמים באושא ואמר סבלונות
העשוין לבלות אין נגבין ושאינן עשוין לבלות נגבין. Vizo halacha he'ela Rabi
Elazar b'Rabi lifnei chachamim b'Usha ve'amar savlanos ha'asuyin livalos ein nigbin veshe'einan
asuyin livalos nigbin.
So exactly that line that we quoted before. Those that are made
to be worn out don't go back, those that are not do
go back. So that sounds מאי לאו אף על גב דלא בלו?
mai lav af al gav d'lo balu? It says עשוין, asuyin, made
to be worn out, right? It doesn't say that have worn out,
but made to be worn out. לא דבלו. Lo d'balu. No, maybe
it means and they got worn out. Again, very bizarre read. תא
שמע, Ta shema, come and hear. סבלונות מועטין שתשתמש בהן והיא בבית
אביה אין נגבין Savlanos muatin shetishtamesh bahen vehi beveit aviha ein nigbin
back to our משנה. Mishna. A few, small amounts that she's going
to use it in her father's house are not collected. Okay, and
that actually sounds that the nature of them is to be used
in her father's house. It doesn't say עשוין לבלות, asuyin livalos, which
you could say means they're made to be worn out and therefore
we're assuming they're worn out. Maybe that's what the גמרא Gemara, was
suggesting. Here it just says are made to be used in the
father's house. Don't reference being worn out. So it sounds like maybe
that they're still around and even though they're still around, they don't
come back because they were made for the father's house. So the
גמרא says תרגמה רבא בביבי וסבכי. Targama Rava beivei v'savchei. So רבא
Rava explained it בביבי וסבכי. beivei v'savchei.
We're talking about like, you know, small types of like a scarf
or, you know, a kerchief or something of that nature which is
very trivial. And that type of a thing, even if it's still
around, but something that's more serious, maybe if it's still around it
does come back. Again, not פשט pshat of any of this. This
certainly did not sound like we were talking about a very narrow
case, sounds like we were talking about a whole class of things.
But that's at least what's being argued, that maybe it will always
go back if it's still around.
Where were we?
Okay. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב מעשה באדם אחד ששיגר לבית חמיו
יין חדש ושמן חדש וכלי פשתן חדש בעצרת. Amar Rav Yehuda amar
Rav ma'aseh b'adam echad sheshigar l'veit chamiv yayin chadash veshemen chadash uchlei
pishtan chadash b'atzeres. Here we have a teaching. A certain person, they
sent to his father-in-law's house new wine and new oil
and new flax garments, silk garments, on
עצרת. Atzeres. All of this was sent on עצרת, Atzeres, okay. So
or I guess it means around עצרת. Atzeres. מאי קמשמע לן? Mai
kamashma lan? So what's the point of telling us this? Okay, he's
on to a new topic. All right. We did not resolve the
עשוין לבלות asuyin livalos versus בלו. balu. Now we just have this
story. It's a very lovely story, but why tell tell us, what's
the הלכה halacha, relevance? אי בעית אימא חשיבות דארץ ישראל קמשמע לן.
I ba'it eima chashivus d'Eretz Yisrael kamashma lan. Maybe it's just telling
us, you know, not everything is הלכה, halacha telling us a nice
story. You should know that in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael it's so
wonderful, they have all of these beautiful,
all of this wine, oil, and all of this stuff is all
already ready even just at עצרת Atzeres time. That's much sooner than
in other lands, that the produce is ready at such an early
time. ואי בעית אימא דאי טעין טענינן ליה. Ve'i ba'it eima d'ei
ta'in taninan leih. Or to tell you that if somebody comes and
says, you know, and says I gave all of these gifts and
it was at שבועות Shavuos time and I gave wine and oil,
you don't say, ah, you're definitely lying. Nobody has wine and oil
ready on שבועות Shavuos time. No, you should know that there was
a story that actually this happened. Of course, even if somebody, it's
not absurd, somebody would still, it's an interesting question of who, where
does the burden of proof lie? But okay. אמר רב יהודה אמר
רב מעשה באדם אחד שאמרו לו אשתו תותראנית היא. Amar Rav Yehuda
amar Rav ma'aseh b'adam echad she'amru lo ishto tutranis hi. A person,
they said to him, your wife is תותראנית, tutranis, the אשתו תותראנית.
ishto tutranis. A person person they said to him, your wife is,
you know, does... not having a good sense of smell. Something that's
occurred to people after COVID. I lost my sense of smell for
about two or three years. My wife had to be the one
to make בורא מיני בשמים borei minei besamim at הבדלה havdala and
now my sense of smell is
back. So anyway, they said to him your wife's sense of smell
is impaired. Now this was a woman, we're going to, there's a
debate how to read this, but we're going to read this, one
version of the רשב"ם, Rashbam, the version of תוספות, Tosafot, that there
already was קידושין, kiddushin, not yet נישואין. nissu'in. Okay.
And this would be considered to be like a מום, mum, a
blemish. And you know, could lead to consequences about divorce without a
כתובה kesubah and all other things that are discussed in כתובות Kesubos
and קידושין. Kiddushin. We're not going to fully worry about that right
now. With you know, does it, what type of מום, mum, you
know, is such bad that it wasn't even the קידושין kiddushin wasn't
even חל, chal, and does it even need a גט, get, which
one needs a גט get but no כתובה. kesubah. But anyway, they
said this to him, okay, that your wife doesn't have a sense
of smell. ונכנס אחריה לחורבה לבודקה. v'nichnas achareiha l'churba l'vodkah. And he
went followed her into like this a desolate place, you know, in
order to test her out. He was going to, he was going
to see whether whether this was true or not. אמר לה Amar
lah ריח צנון אני מריח בגליל. rei'ach tzonan ani meri'ach baGalil. Oh,
you know, apparently they were near the Galilee, and he said oh
you know, I can smell already radishes in the Galilee. And according
he was either hiding a radish under his garment or hiding as
we'll see a you know a date under his garment and seeing
if he could by saying that based on what she would respond,
would she be following his lead and therefore you know or not,
to try to figure out if she knew, you know, if she
was really able to smell what was there. אמרה לו, Amrah lo,
so she said back to him, top of קמ"ו עמוד ב', Kuf
Mem Vav amud Bais, מאן יהיב לן מכותבות יריחו ואכילנא בה. man
yeiv lan mikosvos Yericho v'achilna bei. Oh, if only, nice that you're
smelling radishes, if only we would be able to smell from the
you know or have the pressed dates of יריחו, Yericho, יריחו עיר
תמרים, Yericho Ir Temarim, that's what I would love to eat because
you know go you know I like sort of like sharp together
with sweet and dates would go well with your radishes. So okay,
not exactly clear you know what was going on, but the רשב"ם
Rashbam says it was pretty clear she was onto him. Alright. So
anyway, whatever it was, we don't know whether he did prove his
point or didn't prove his point. That's not the issue. Let's see
where the גמרא goes with this.
נפל עליה חורבה ומתה. nafal aleiha churba umesa. And then the ruin
fell on her, the the house, and she died. So the question
here is, and now he wanted to inherit her. So the question
is, a husband doesn't inherit his wife after קידושין, kiddushin, only after
נישואין. nissu'in. So he was claiming, I'm going to read this תוספות'
Tosafos way, apparently this was his property, and he was claiming look
I took her into my property, and therefore she's my wife, and
the הלכה halacha? is after קידושין kiddushin if a woman goes into
a husband's property with a purpose of נישואין, nissu'in, then that constitutes
חופה chuppah and נישואין nissu'in and she's his wife, full wife, and
he would inherit her. So אמרו חכמים, amru chachamim, but the sages
said, הואיל ולא נכנס אחריה אלא לבודקה, ho'il v'lo nichnas achareiha ella
l'vodkah, מצטערני, mitzta'arni, sorry Charlie, you know, you were not doing it,
it was quite the opposite, you were questioning whether you were going
to go through with the wedding, there was no way that this
was a going into your property for the purpose of נישואין, nissu'in,
so therefore you do not inherit her, there was no נישואין nissu'in
took place. Okay, not again, not exactly clear what it has to
do with the גמרא, but it sort of is, you know, dying
between that space between אירוסין eirusin and נישואין. nissu'in. We'll just finish
up to the משנה Mishnah for today. סבלונות מרובין שתישתמש בהן בבית
אביה. sevlonos merubin shetishtamesh bahen b'veis aviha. יתיב רבין סבא. Yosiv Ravin
Sava. So
here the משנה Mishnah makes a distinction between a lot or a
little as opposed to the nature of them, whether they're normally worn
out or not. יתיב רבין סבא, Yosiv Ravin Sava, so Ravin the
Elder sat קמיה דרב פפא, kamei d'Rav Pappa, ויתיב וקאמר, v'yosiv v'ka'amar,
בין שמתה היא ובין שמת הוא, bein shemesa hi uvein shemes hu,
הדר, hadar, or הדר הוא hadar hu סבלונות הדרי. sevlonos hadrei. Now
we were talking about whether you know there was he ate בבית
חמיו b'veis chamiv or not, but the also question is you know
why is the wedding being called off, why is it not going
through with it, and whose fault was it?
So he says you know when the things are going to go
back, either we're talking about the סבלונות sevlonos that are not usually
worn out, or whether we're talking about the סבלונות sevlonos that are
you know worn out but he didn't eat בבית אביה. b'veis aviha.
Okay, and now they're going to go back. So he says certainly
that would be when they go back, all the scenarios we spoke
about, either אינה עשויה ליבלות eina asuya l'balos or עשויה ליבלות asuya
l'balos without the meal. Okay, that is certainly applies to a case
of whether he died or she died, she died or he died,
or
or or he was the one that backed out. So בין שמת
הוא bein shemes hu הדר הוא hadar hu סבלונות הדרי. sevlonos hadrei.
מאכל ומשתה לא הדרי. ma'achal umishteh lo hadrei. The סבלונות sevlonos go
back, the food and the drink do not go back.
Let me say that again. I'm not sure I said that right.
This is in the scenario where he where he did eat
the food and he did eat in his father-in-law's house. And therefore
what's the הלכה? halacha The הלכה is that the אין עשויין לבלות
ein asuyin livalot go back and the עשויין לבלות, asuyin livalot, the
best example of that would be food that does not come back
within if he ate the סעודת חתן. seudat chatan. That's what we
said when he ate the סעודת חתן, seudat chatan, the stuff that
was expected to stay in the father-in-law's house and a prime example
would be food, that he does not get back if something happens
to the wedding. So now we're going to talk about but what
if it was her fault? And we're going to say that if
it was her fault,
then even the food goes back. So let's read that again. יתיב
רבין סבא קמיה דרב פפא יתיב וקאמר Yativ Ravin Sava kamei deRav
Pappa yativ veka'amar בין שמת הוא bein shemeisa hu בין שמתה היא
bein shemeisa hi בין שמת הוא, bein shemeisa hu, whether she died
or he died or הדר הוא hadar hu or he broke off
the wedding, and then and it was the case that he ate
בבית חמיו, bveiss chamiv, so סבלונות הדרי, savlonot hadri, the סבלונות savlonot
that go back, the things that would אין עשויין לבלות ein asuyin
livalot would go back, מיכל ומשתי לא הדרי, meichol u'mishtay lo hadri,
the food and the drink that doesn't go back, that's the rule,
עשויין לבלות asuyin livalot doesn't go back. But here's the חידוש. chidush.
הדרה בה איהי, hadra ba ee hi,
if she says I'm not going through with the נישואין, nisuin, she
breaks it off, so it's not just she died, she's to blame,
she breaks it off, I mean not necessarily it was a bad
decision, but anyway it was her decision. In that case, הדרא אפילו
כישורא דירקא, hadra afilu kishara d'yarka, then even a bundle of vegetables
go back.
Even if he ate בבית חמיו bveiss chamiv and even if it's
something totally that was consumed and even if it was the food
he brought and they already ate, since she broke it off, that
has to get repaid. Now אמר רב יהודה אמר רב הונא בריה
דרב יהושע Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav Huna brei deRav Yehoshua ושמין
להן v'shamin lahen דמי בשר בזול, d'mei basar b'zol, and but you
don't figure it based on
the price that he paid but the price of cheap meat. So
if he went ahead and he brought them these like steaks, prime
steaks, and gave it to them, now they have to repay, but
how much do they repay? Not the price of steaks but of
cheap meat, of like skirt steaks or of like
hamburger. עד כמה עד תילתא, ad kama ad tilsa, that's figure it
to be a third less than what he paid. This is a
general principle that if somebody eats food
that they didn't steal it and under a reason to assume that
they had a right to eat it and then it turns out
that they didn't have a right to eat it and they benefited,
you know they can always sort of say how much did they
benefit? Well they had a fifty dollar steak but I never would
have bought for myself a fifty dollar steak, I would have paid
for myself twenty dollars. So when you figure out what I benefited
and therefore I owe you since I didn't steal it, you figure
it out on a different basis. That's the basic חידוש chidush here
that if she chooses and it was her choice everything has to
be repaid but if it was food that was eaten it's computed
at a slightly different rate. We will end for here.